On 19th of September 2017 a 7.1 magnitude earthquake shook the nation of Mexico
causing the collapse of many buildings and resulting in 370 fatalities and 6,000 injuries.
The devastating earthquake left thousands homeless and desperate without water, food or electricity
and grieving the loss of loved ones that did not survive.
Moved by compassion, Prophet TB Joshua sent the Emmanuel TV team and partners
to the affected areas in Mexico to bring help to the helpless and hope to the hopeless.
Join us in this love work as we reach out to the people of Mexico, knowing that as Christians
we are called to respond to all human needs.
The Emmanuel TV Earthquake Relief
Mexico
A magnitude-7.1 earthquake shook central Mexico on September the 19th, 2017
striking suddenly and leaving nothing, but destruction in its wake.
The Emmanuel TV Earthquake Relief Team sent by TB Joshua and the Emmanuel TV partners worldwide
to assist with the survivors and search and rescue teams who are racing against time to save lives
had arrived in Mexico city the day after the central earthquake.
The officers in the green uniforms explained that the first need was to transport some food and water
which had been donated to a local reception center to one of the emergency medical centers in the city.
The Emmanuel TV vehicles pull up and are quickly loaded with the fresh food, bread and water
for the emergency medical center on the other side of the city and as fast as possible
the team were off to deliver their precious cargo at the Medical Center.
Volunteers spring into action alongside the team to get them much-needed water and food to those who need it,
both those working in the search an -rescue mission and those being rescued
from the rubble of crushed buildings.
Emmanuel TV Team Transports Food And Water For The Emergency Rescue Center
While delivering supplies to the emergency medical center, the doctors there explained an urgent need
to send some medical supplies to one particular search and rescue zone
and they asked the Emmanuel TV team's help.
These are some of the supplies to be delivered to the wanting search and rescue zone -
medical fluids, medications, pain killers, neck collars, first aid essentials
and equipment for treating and dressing wounds.
Emmanuel TV Assists Doctors To Carry Emergency Medical Supplies For Search And Rescue Teams
Led by one of the doctors the Emmanuel TV team arrives in the search and rescue zone.
Getting as close as they can by car, they take the supplies and continue on foot
making their way through the streets to the temporary store.
Emmanuel TV Assists Doctors To Carry Emergency Medical Supplies For Search And Rescue Teams
Everywhere you can see volunteers wearing masks and hard hats as safety precautions,
as they are organized into groups to help with the rescue work.
On arrival at the scene, the rescue workers were making arrangements to have light and generators
to enable them to work into the night, as the time is short for those trapped in the wreckage.
Several 20 litre kegs are purchased by the Emmanuel TV team and here they fill them with the necessary fuel
and return to the search and rescue zone.
The Emmanuel TV Team Buys And Delivers Fuel For Search And Rescue Lighting Generators
The work was still going on strong as they carry the fuel into the building sites
where the generators were being set up.
The Emmanuel TV Team Buys And Delivers Fuel For Search And Rescue Lighting Generators
Meanwhile, the industrial crane hoists a huge slab of concrete rubble away from the rescue zone.
But while the world's attention is on the capital city, many in poor villages in the south of Mexico
which were devastated by the even stronger 8.2 magnitude earthquake on the 7th of September
are still struggling.
So the Emmanuel TV team decides to make the long journey by road to Oaxaca state to lend a helping hand.
So having seen the plight of our brothers and sisters in Oaxaca state,
an Emmanuel TV team here in Mexico city is now preparing for the very long journey
carrying with us more than 500 boxes ready to be packed full of food and hygiene supplies
for the affected families down in Oaxaca state.
As TB Joshua has taught us:
"God blesses us not only that we may earn a living, but so that we are able to give".
The Journey From Mexico City To Oaxaca State
The Emmanual TV team has arrived here in southern Oaxaca state in Mexico,
the area which was devastated by the massive earthquake on the 7th of September.
The team is here going to collect and pack the food and the hygiene items into the over 500 multi-purpose boxes.
The families in this area in 3 different villages are waiting for help.
As TB Joshua has taught us: "Someone is waiting for you for a lifetime".
"Failing them is failing God."
Purchasing The Bulk Food And Hygiene Supplies From A Wholesale Warehouse
The Emmanuel TV team moves straight to a wholesale warehouse in the nearest large town in Oaxaca state
to pay for and collect the pre-ordered food and hygiene supplies for the earthquake survivors and rescue teams.
The warehouse crew used trolleys and forklift trucks to load the large pallets of pre-ordered goods
for the Emmanuel TV Earthquake Relief into the delivery lorry.
Purchasing The Bulk Food And Hygiene Supplies From A Wholesale Warehouse
This truck was provided by a local businessman to the Emmanuel TV team to help in the transportation
of the supplies from the warehouse to the affected areas.
The loading process begins - first with the large weighty pallets and plastic wrapped cartons,
then with individual boxes and cartons of supplies,
to make sure as much as possible can be contained in the trucks.
The process repeats for the second truck, stacking the items as high as they can go,
until there is no more space left.
Now loaded full of essential food and hygiene supplies, the Emmanuel TV team sets off on their journey
to Juchitán, where the aid will be distributed to over 500 families that have been affected by the earthquake.
The Emmanuel TV Trucks Transport Food And Hygiene Supplies To The Temporary Logistics Centre
Arriving in Juchitan the vehicles enter the compound that will be used as a logistic center
to sort, pack and store the supplies for distribution to the needy villages.
Inside the base, Mexican volunteers assist the Emmanuel TV team to set out
the multi-purpose plastic boxes which will be given out one per family,
filled with the food and essential hygiene ítems brought from the warehouse.
While the colorful boxes were being set out, another group brings down the products from the trucks.
A last step before the boxes are filled is to decorate them with in an 'Emmanuel TV Disaster Relief' sticker.
These are the 500 boxes that will be given to families in the state of Oaxaca,
affected by the magnitude-8.2 earthquake.
Hello and good morning. We are here in Juchitan, in the State of Oaxaca,
in one of the municipalities affected by the earthquake of 7th September 2017.
As you can see behind me, we have here the food which will shortly be distributed
and packed into plastic boxes to take directly to those families with so much need.
Now the job of sorting out the different products and sharing them into the boxes begins.
Forming a chain the team swiftly sends the items along from the tables and places them into the waiting boxes.
The Food And Hygiene Supplies Are Packed Into The Over 500 Multi-Purpose Plastic Boxes
They start with some of the bulky items like storage boxes, paper towels and detergent
before adding tin foods cooking oil and other hygiene products. The momento note of encouragement reads:
"Remember that there is always Someone praying for you. You are not alone."
As we can see, the team is continuing to work to fill these boxes with basic food
and hygiene products that will be delivered to those families who are waiting for us.
Also Emmanuel TV has thought to reach these hearts and homes
with a small memento translated in the Huave language saying,
"Remember that there is always Someone praying for you. You are not alone".
After a good effort, the five hundred boxes have been filled with love and enough supplies
to make a big difference in the lives of those who will receive them.
The difficulties imposed by the powerful earthquake just over a week ago are still very much being felt
in the disadvantaged villages and areas of southern Oaxaca.
The Emmanuel TV Food And Hygiene Boxes Prepared For Earthquake Victims
With everything ready at last the Emmanuel TV team sets off early the next day to two different villages -
first San Mateo del Mar, an indigenous seaside fishing community
and Chi Kappa de Castro, an inland farming community a little further north.
The level of devastation on the lower quality structures from the quake,
which was over five hundred times more powerful than the one which hit Mexico city cannot be hidden.
The Emmanuel TV Team At The Earthquake Damaged Areas In Oaxaca State, Mexico
My name is Jason nd my whole house fell down in the earthquake -
all our clothes are under the rubbles of the walls.
Material things do not matter; what matters is life and we are fine.
While many families lost their homes, their possessions and their livelihoods, some even lost their lives,
a bold sentiment from one so young but a sentiment that seemed shared among the villagers
who have already started doing what they can to pick up the pieces, clean up the mess the earthquake left behind
and get back to normal life again.
The Emmanuel TV Team At The Earthquake Damaged Areas In Oaxaka State, Mexico
Here the Emmanuel TV team is led into the homes of some of the villagers to see the extent
of what the earthquake did - heavy furniture lies where the quake had thrown them down
and large cracks may be seen even in the concrete floor.
The Emmanuel TV Team At The Earthquake Damaged Areas In Oaxaka State, Mexico
Families Gather To Receive The Emmanuel TV Food And Hygiene Relief
Families from the villages gather to meet the Emmanuel TV team and receive from them the much-needed food,
hygiene supplies provided as an expression of love and solidarity by TB Joshua and the Emmanuel TV partners.
Everybody from grandparents to grandchildren happily form a line as the preparations are made
for the distribution to begin. From the chairs scattered around you can tell they have been expecting
the arrival of the team with some excitement and are glad of the good news
that someone has been thinking about them, and that some relief has finally come.
The Emmanuel TV team sees it as a privilege to be in a position to help,
guided by the words of TB Joshua that giving is a real privilege, if it is done in a proper attitude.
Those who are strong enough, take the boxes themselves with a heat and a smile,
while the elderly or weaker members of the community are assisted by the volunteers.
The Emmanuel TV Food And Hygiene Relief Boxes Are Presented To Needy Family
The grateful families express their thanks for the provisions, which will go a long way to meet their needs
in these trying times.
The team takes a moment to explain to this elderly woman the contents of the box she's receiving
and she nods with satisfaction.
The expression of their faces encourages those waiting on the line that it is well worth the wait.
More and more families receive the food and hygiene gift boxes and express both their surprise and thanks
for both the gift freely given and the hearts behind it.
The Emmanuel TV Food And Hygiene Relief Boxes Are Presented To Needy Family
Many thanks to the organization that made possible this great gift
that the people of Chicapa really needed. Thank you very much.
Olivia Avasolo
San Mateo del Mar
Thanks for the support. The earthquake damaged our house
and many people have nowhere to live, nowhere to stay.
Thank you for the pantry.
Margarita Villasenor Valverda
San Mateo del Mar
Thank you Emmanuel TV!
Araceli Salomon
San Mateo del Mar
My experience in the earthquake is something horrible.
I could not go out with my children, I had to stay there locked up with my two little ones.
I believed that at that moment the house was going to fall down.
Everything began to fall down and all I could do was to hold my children
and give them refuge in my arms.
We just prayed and thanked God that He would cover and protect us.
Many thanks Emmanuel TV for this opportunity and for this support that you have sent us
here in the village of "Ikoots" people. Many thanks from my heart.
I receive this on behalf of my mother and I thank God for remembering us
and may God give you more.
It is hard for me to speak about it because I lost my father.
I thank God that you are here supporting us; many thanks and may God give you all long life.
Catalina Sanchez de la Rosa
Chicapa de Castro
Thank you Emmanuel TV!
My name is Jacinto Orozco Sanchez and I am with my family receiving this relief
due to the earthquake that we went through. It was a nightmare for us.
We give thanks to Emmanuel TV for this support, which for us is very significant
since in these times we are going through many difficult things.
The Villagers Gladly Taking Away Their Food And Hygiene Relief Donated By Emmanuel TV
Some families traveled quite a distance from the surrounding areas
and hearing that the Emmanuel TV Earthquake Relief team was coming.
Happily, they bought different vehicles able to return home with a degree of satisfaction
for their successful journey.
Others who live nearby take the stroll home proudly holding their gift boxes for all to see
and others wait in the shade for their transportation.
It is amazing to see the impact a simple gift can bring. For love is a language that transcends all boundaries,
understood by both young and old alike.
The Villagers Gladly Taking Away Their Food And Hygiene Relief Donated By Emmanuel TV
Thank you Prophet TB Joshua!
My name is Arcelia Lopez Garcia.
Thank You very much Lord for Your blessings
My whole life I owe it to You
As You take care of the birds
My whole life depends on You
I thank You Lord for Your favours
My whole life I owe it to You
As You take care of the birds
My whole life depends on You
Thank You Emmanuel TV!
Villager From Chicapa de Castro Explains Her Loss Of Livelihood
Leticia Lopez Orozco
Chicapa de Castro
I lost my pot and part of my house in the earthquake.
I was making tortillas for a living to support my children
because my husband is a farmer and he has almost no work,
so we were living from that with my five children.
The Emmanuel TV Team At The Earthquake Damaged Areas In Oaxaca State, Mexico
Emanuel Santiago
Chicapa de Castro
This project idea was born after the severe earthquake here in Chicapa de Castro.
Many families were left without a livelihood following damage to the ovens they used
for hand-made tortillas which are a local speciality product
that generates employment here in the village.
The oven basically consists of a large pot in which the tortillas are made,
first kneading them and then sticking them to the edges of the pot
at a high temperature until the tortillas are cooked.
We need one hundred new ovens to reactivate the economy of Chicapa de Castro
and one hundred families will benefit from this.
So the Emmanuel TV team has heard about the wonderful project which you're doing
to restart the economy here in the village of Chicapa de Castro by providing the pot oven liners,
so that people can start to make the tortillas and earn a living again.
On behalf of T.B. Joshua and the Emmanuel TV partners we'd like to sponsor 100 of these pottery oven liners
and it would give us great pleasure therefore to present you with thirty-five thousand pesos
for the manufacture of the oven liners and for the transport.
Many thanks for this assistance because it is going to benefit many families here in Chicapa de Castro.
With all my heart, many thanks Emmanuel TV.
Thank you for your help with all my heart, Emmanuel TV.
The Location Of Santa Maria Del Mar Accessible Only By Sea
The next port of call was Santa Maria Del Mar,
a secluded village community accessible only by water. On the way to Santa Maria Del Mar
the team traverse a rough track to the shoreline where the boats have been arranged to take the team across
to another area affected by the earthquake that has received little or no assistance at all.
The Departure Point For Boats To Santa Maria Del Mar
Just as Jesus Christ himself is the solution to the problems of all mankind,
so He expects us to be a solution to someone in trouble.
This is a coastal area of Oaxaca state known as El Faro,
where the boats come to take people to a very remote and isolated village called Santa Maria Del Mar
and the Emmanuel TV team right now is preparing to take boxes with food and hygiene provisions
to this isolated community.
The Loading Of Boats For Santa Maria Del Mar With The Emmanuel TV Food And Hygiene Boxes
The Emmanuel TV team's vehicle reverses into a good position to allow the team to load
the precious cargo of food and hygiene supplies into the boat for transportation across the sea.
Everybody lends a hand to get the scores of colourful boxes
of much-needed supplies properly stowed in the boats.
The well-worn wooden slats make a good platform for wedging the boxes squarely into the boat,
so that they won't topple over during the voyage.
The Emmanuel TV team forms a chain with the local fishermen to quickly pass the boxes into the boats
and as the saying goes: "Many hands make light work."
The Loading Of Boats For Santa Maria Del Mar With The Emmanuel TV Food And Hygiene Boxes
With the boats loaded up, they are covered in a thick green tarpaulin to protect the relief boxes
and their precious contents from the elements. Finally, fastening the whole thing securely with strong ropes
the boats were ready to depart for Santa Maria Del Mar.
A light rain began to fall as the team pushes off from the shore.
The Loading Of Boats For Santa Maria Del Mar With The Emmanuel TV Food And Hygiene Boxes
The fishermen navigate the beautiful, clear waters of the Pacific Ocean, as we head to the remote village.
In different circumstances the surroundings could make for a perfect holiday getaway
but after the violence of the earthquake, the isolation from the rest of the world
just makes help all the harder to come by.
The Emmanuel TV Team And Relief Boxes On The Boat Journey To Santa Maria Del Mar
Traveling in tandem, the boats move as fast as the heavy load of cargo and passengers can permit.
To clear the vast expanse of water the shore leading to the village comes into view on the horizon
and the boats reduce their speed as they near the land.
The Emmanuel TV Team And Relief Boxes On The Boat Journey To Santa Maria Del Mar
The expert fishermen maneuver the boats close to the shore to make a good approach for a safe landing.
Largely untouched the rustic setting boasts of only a few boats moored nearby.
As the first boat pulls gently onto the shore, the rain which had been their companion over the sea softens.
The Emmanuel TV Team Arrives At Santa Maria Del Mar
Unloading Of The Emmanuel TV Relief Boxes At Santa Maria Del Mar
As the rain gradually dies down, the team once again form a chain
and pass the earthquake relief boxes quickly ashore stacking them high in the waiting vehicles.
Amazed at the effort of the team to reach the community
villagers are glad to assist in bringing the boxes out of the boats and loading them up.
Unloading Of The Emmanuel TV Relief Boxes At Santa Maria Del Mar
Let's hear the experience of the night of the earthquake from one of the indigents of Santa Maria Del Mar.
Ciro Gonzalez Martinez
Santa Maria Del Mar
On September 7th, at about 10:30 pm we felt like a roar from this Pacific Ocean.
It felt very strong; my family were going to sleep when the sea suddenly gave a great long roar!
Everyone panicked and at that time, we were looking for how to get out of the house.
We heard noise and children crying and many fences and houses had collapsed
but I thank God that nothing serious happened to us, even though we live in an isolated village.
At this time, we thank Prophet T.B. Joshua and the Emmanuel TV Partners for collaborating
and donating, for giving their heart to Santa Maria Del Mar; we are very grateful.
The Emmanuel TV Team Journeys To The Village In Santa Maria Del Mar
A beautiful blue hue has returned to the skies, as the Emmanuel TV team
are driven along the winding path to the village community.
On arrival, help is at hand to unload the relief boxes as quickly as possible.
Unloading The Emmanuel TV Food And Hygiene Relief Boxes
For outside, word of the Emmanuel TV team's arrival, has traveled fast
and already a line of people has formed to meet them and see what is going on.
More and more large families come on foot from the corners of the region.
Despite the recent disaster, the arrival of the Emmanuel TV team brings with it
an atmosphere of joy and happiness.
Families Gather To Receive The Emmanuel TV Food And Hygiene Relief
And the residents smile and wave for the camera, as they await the proceedings to get underway.
Even the children are happy at all the excitement in their rural home.
Just as in the other communities: one big box of food and hygiene items is given per family
with some assistance on hand to help the weaker or more aged members of the community
to carry theirs home with them. Grateful receiving like gracious giving comes from the heart
and the expression on their faces says it all:
Thank you, Jesus Christ for remembering us in our time of need.
The Emmanuel TV Food And Hygiene Relief Boxes Are Presented To The Needy Families
As the families lined up, the Emmanuel TV team took time to speak with some of them
to hear what had happened to them and their beloved village during the quake. Let's listen to a few of them.
The Emmanuel TV Food And Hygiene Relief Boxes Are Presented To The Needy Families
Nailea Martinez Jimenez
Santa Maria Del Mar
The day of the earthquake tragedy, was the day we thought would be our last day on earth
but thanks to God we are alive.
Thank you to Emmanuel TV for the relief box that you have brought us.
Azael Gonzalez Luis
Santa Maria Del Mar
My experience with the earthquake was a very frightening night for me and my family.
I have two children - one is 10 years old, the other is 4 years old and my wife is pregnant.
On that day we were sleeping when the earthquake began.
The door got stuck and we could not leave the house.
I couldn´t leave my house and I couldn't do anything except have faith in God!
I thank Emmanuel TV and Prophet T.B. Joshua for visiting us,
traveling a very long distance to reach this village, which as you can see is in the middle of the sea.
Thank you Emmanuel TV for the relief boxes and for coming to give a moment of happiness
to the children, women and especially to the village of Santa Maria Del Mar.
Local Women Prepare A Community Meal With Ingredients Provided By Emmanuel TV
The Emmanuel TV team also provided ingredients for the community to have a big meal together
following the distribution of the food and hygiene relief boxes.
Women of the region joyfully prepare the feast together, some making the special tortilla bread
in the traditional way sticking the dough to the round oven like pots,
while on the other side of the kitchen a large vat of rice
dotted with colorful slices of vegetables is simmering away nicely.
This woman keeps an experiencd eye on some beautifully seasoned shrimp
stirring it gently, just a little while longer, and the celebration will begin.
Local Women Prepare A Community Meal With Ingredients Provided By Emmanuel TV
Doesn't that look good? Big spoonfuls of rice are heaped upon the plates
with a generous helping of the chicken sauce.
Local juice is served alongside the meal to wash it all down with.
The Emmanuel TV Team Shares A Meal With The Community In Santa Maria Del Mar
With a smile, the Emmanuel TV team takes delight in serving the people with a good hot meal,
while some groups serve out the rice,
others serve the tortilla bread and with healthy dollops of the spicy green sauce are local favorite.
The Emmanuel TV Team Shares A Meal With The Community In Santa Maria Del Mar
After the lovely meal and excitement of the day's event the children of Santa Maria Del Mar had this to say:
Thank you, TB Joshua for visiting us. We love you! Thank you, Emmanuel TV! Yay!
RV: Pavel Tatyana Zheleznyakov 27/04/2019